Guide to the Stanford University, Department of Psychology, Honors Theses
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Department of Psychology, honors theses
1976-2005
SC4-4519
Stanford University. Department of Psychology.
1.75 Linear feet (75 volumes)
Honors theses written by undergraduates in the Stanford University Dept. of Psychology.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Theses were transferred to the Stanford University Archives from the Hume Writing Center in 2011.
Information about Access
The collection is open for research use; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use. No photocopies may be made.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of honors theses written by undergraduates in the Stanford University Dept. of Psychology.
Access Terms
Psychology--Study and teaching.; Student papers.
Collection Contents
- Theses, Accession ARCH-2011-152
  - Bounds, Ryan Wesley, The counterbiasing effect of clearly flawed one-sided arguments., undated [1995] (Box 1)
  - Cabading, Paula-Ann, The role of interpersonal goals in interactional satisfaction., 1996 (Box 1)
  - Coda-Nunziante, Paola, In and out of the maze: the effects of a biased time orientation on cognitive and motivational aspects of problem-solving., 1985 (Box 1)
  - Crean, Klara Strasikova, The role of intonation in communication with infants: an analysis of responses to prosodic and semantic cues., 1998 (Box 1)
  - Dickerson, Chris Ann, Some effects of attributional style on interpersonal living., 1986 (Box 1)
  - Flexner, Lisa M., Making work fun: effects of task presentation on intrinsic motivation in preschool children., 1994 (Box 1)
  - Forehand, Mark, Volunteer motivations: a functional analysis of the decision to volunteer., 1992 (Box 1)
  - Fry, Jeanne, Sex differences in adolescent depression and attributional style., 1994 (Box 1)
  - Honigberg, Diane, Factors affecting the perceptions of bias in balanced media presentations., 1988 (Box 1)
  - Jollett, Mikel, Stereotype threat and the academic disidentification of African-American students., 1996 (Box 1)
  - Kinder, Eric, Uncertainty as a factor in the ruminative response to depression., 1992 (Box 1)
  - Lawrence, Laura Lynn, Melodies and lyrics in speech: an analysis of young children's behavioral responses to prosodic and semantic vocal cues., 1992 (Box 1)
  - Lee, Jennifer, Conceptualization of time through spatial metaphors: front/back and up/down metaphors in Chinese., 1998 (Box 1)
  - Mattes, Melinda, The importance of body image in determining an individual's trait satisfaction., 1999 (Box 1)
  - Nelson, Leif D., The reversal of defensive processing through self-affirmation., 1998 (Box 1)
  - Osofsky, Michael J., The psychological experience of security officers who work with executions., 2003 (Box 1)
  - Penaz, Jane, Adult influences in the development of explanatory style in children., 1988 (Box 1)
  - Ramon, Ana-Christina, To identify or disidentify? The negative consequences of a positive group stereotype among Latino and white students., 1998 (Box 1)
  - Sherman, Bonnie Rae, The effect of education on attitudes about rape and sex-roles., 1987 (Box 1)
  - Sullivan, Sarah, You never lose the ages you've been: how age facilitates perspective taking ability in an affective domain., 2005 (Box 1)
  - Wahl, Kelly E., Message design for the primary prevention of AIDS., 1988 (Box 1)
  - Wang, Oliver, Squirrel monkey HPA activity after removal of cortisol feedback during social separation., 1997 (Box 1)
  - Weisz, Carolyn, The relationship between time perspective and unplanned pregnancy among teenage women., 1987 (Box 1)
  - Abrahams, Matthew, Total involvement., 1991 (Box 2)
  - DeBell, Megan A., A functional magnetic resonance imaging assessment of the role of mental rotation in object processing., undated [1996?] (Box 2)
  - Eckstrand, Jeffrey, Maternal regulation of the hypothalamic-pituitary adrenal axis in response to stress in infant rats., 1991 (Box 2)
  - Epel, Elissa Sarah, Time perspective, self-efficacy, and homelessness., 1990 (Box 2)
  - Hansen, Kristin E., Young children's understanding of the mediation of the mind in emotions: emotional change as a result of cognitive cueing., 1993 (Box 2)
  - Isaacowitz, Derek Martin, Socioemotional selectivity in the adult development of trauma survivors., 1996 (Box 2)
  - Lin, Nancy T., Children's knowledge about unconsciousness., 1996 (Box 2)
  - Luppen, Cynthia Alice, Motivations for cigarette smoking and cessation among Stanford students., 1996 (Box 2)
  - Levin, Rachel, Sterotypes make the difference: gender differences in performance and partipation in computer science., 1996 (Box 2)
  - Shi, Alice, The role of shape and taxonomy in children's word-learning and inductive inferences., 1996 (Box 2)
  - Rios, Kimberly M., To be or not to be the 'model minority': positive stereotypes and the mathematical performance of targets and nontargets., 2003 (Box 2)
  - Moyers, Michael, Control of forbidden information: influence of "insider" information on investment decisions., 1988 (Box 2)
  - Haydel, Angela M., Self-affirmation: implications for anchoring and adjustment., 1996 (Box 2)
  - Pfeifer, Jennifer, Racial awareness and contact: factors in children's development of the own-race bias in face recognition., 2000 (Box 2)
  - Lo, Gilbert, The dilution of objective feedback with social comparison information: a study of happy and unhappy people., 1993 (Box 2)
  - Emerzian, Michael, Emotional experience in the presence of others: does having someone around chase away the blues?., 1989 (Box 2)
  - Chan, Theresa, Self-help groups for depression: an application of the response-styles theory., 1990 (Box 2)
  - Drake, Michael, Is laughter realy the best medicine? Humor as a strategy fo coping with negative elements., 1993 (Box 2)
  - Abbott, Kristin, Children's understanding of intention as a mental representation., 1994 (Box 2)
  - O'Neil, Jennifer, The effects of race and racial stereotypicality on perceptions of crime and mental illness., 2005 (Box 2)
  - Toosi, Negin, Dangerous moves: perceptions of threat, aggression, and stereotypicality for Black and White movement., 2003 (Box 2)
  - Dudokovic, Nicole M., Telling a story versus telling it straight: the effects of accurate and entertaining retellings on memory., 2000 (Box 2)
  - Tsai, Jeanne L., Social interaction with the elderly: a comparison of Caucasian and Chinese-American students., 1991 (Box 3)
  - Ryan, Sharon, Questions and rising-pitch terminals in Japanese and English infant-directed speech., 1991 (Box 3)
  - Cummings, Alycia Erin, Does isolated word presentation promote infant word learning?., 2000 (Box 3)
  - Allen, Angelina C., Eating practices and disordered eating: a comparative study of French and American adolescents., 2000 (Box 3)
  - Asgari, Maryam, Infants' perception of musical phrase structure., 1992 (Box 3)
  - Subramanian, Asha P., Lost, then found: implicit memory for nonreal objects., 1994 (Box 3)
  - Fox, Caroline MeiMei, The effects of interdependence and independence on emotional contagion: a cross-cultural study., 1994 (Box 3)
  - Cawthon, Stephanie, Grammatical acquisition in moderately to profoundly hearing impaired children., 1994 (Box 3)
  - Bedell, Brian T., Existential concern, confrontation, and skepticism: personality variables reflecting human approaches to the humanly unanswerable., 1994 (Box 3)
  - Miners, Leah M., Infant preference for repetition in speech., 1994 (Box 3)
  - Baird, Jodie A., Young children's understanding of what strangers know about each other., 1995 (Box 3)
  - Sung, Janet M., Validation goal conflict: its occurrence and impact among Asian-Americans., 1993 (Box 3)
  - Suzuki, Lalita K., Gender and ethnicity as factors in childhood identity., 1993 (Box 3)
  - Ward, Jennifer, An intervention to affect progress and satisfaction following knee surgery., 1995 (Box 3)
  - Phelps, Molly A., Prevalence and impact of trauma in a nonclinical population., 1995 (Box 3)
  - Seja, Astrida L., Children's understanding of thought controllability., 1995 (Box 3)
  - Majd, Katayoon, Alternating between selves: effects of biculturalism on Asian-American self-concept., 1995 (Box 3)
  - Edelman, Gabriel, Are int_rn_lly gen_rat_d memories less associated with context than externally presented memories?., 1998 (Box 3)
  - Kaomea, Julie, Adapting to diversity in the classroom: how to motivate those students who "just can't compete"., 1989 (Box 3)
  - Shih, Margaret, Individual differences in the tendency to categorize., 1994 (Box 3)
  - Gross, Erika L., The influence of labels on 12-month-olds' attention to objects., 1994 (Box 3)
  - Garcia, Stephen Michael, Ethnic and social class differences in interpersonal sensitivity: accuracy effects of subordinate roles., 1995 (Box 3)
  - Pelisari, Krista, Understanding the development of children's mental rotation ability: an fMRI study., 2001 (Box 3)
  - Mikami, Amori Yee, The effect of dieting on the persistence of dysphoria among early adolescent females., 1998 (Box 3)
  - Chu, Joyce, Effects of East Asian culture on emotion physiology and experience of major depressive disorder., 2000 (Box 3)
  - Rosen, Daniel J., Discrimination and reversal of the rabbit's nictitating membrane response with mossy fiber stimulation as a conditioned stimulus., 1986 (Box 3)
  - Koven, Deborah, Ruminative and distracting responses to depression and their effects on interpretations and attributions., 1992 (Box 3)
- Theses from Zimbardo papers, 1976, 1985; Accession ARCH.2012-023
  These honors theses were transferred from the Philip G. Zimbardo Papers (Stanford University Archives collection number SC0750).
  - Tong, Debra Y. F., Interview interactions between shy and non-shy persons., 1976 (Box 1)
  - Davis, Hilary R., Cognitive and behavioral components of shyness., 1976 (Box 1)
  - Warren, M. Luann, Time to create: an empirical investigation of dispositional and situational determinants of creativity., 1985 (Box 1)